<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>privacy-book</title><id>https://mako088.github.io/atom3.xml</id><updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><link href="https://mako088.github.io/atom3.xml" rel="self"/><link href="https://mako088.github.io/atom2.xml" rel="prev"/><subtitle>An mdBook-generated site</subtitle><entry><title>Hardening Networking</title><id>https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_networking.html</id><updated>2025-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><link href="https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_networking.html" rel="alternate"/><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Hardening Networking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NetworkManagers global config is &lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/NetworkManager.conf&lt;/code&gt;.
Additional config files can be placed in &lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/conf.d&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After editing a config file, apply the changes with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo nmcli general reload
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo usermod -aG network $USER
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Investigate sockets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Display all TCP Sockets with service names:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;ss -at
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Display all TCP Sockets with port numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;ss -atn
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Display all UDP Sockets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;ss -au
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Configure NetworkManager to use Quad9s DoT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/Wi-Fi.nmconnection&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-.nmconnection&quot;&gt;[connection]
dns-over-tls=2

[ipv4]
dns=9.9.9.9#dns.quad9.net;149.112.112.112#dns.quad9.net;
ignore-auto-dns=true

[ipv6]
dns=2620:fe::fe#dns.quad9.net;2620:fe::9#dns.quad9.net;
ignore-auto-dns=true
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo systemctl restart NetworkManager
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wi-Fi MAC randomization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the following to &lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/conf.d/wifi_rand_mac.conf&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-conf&quot;&gt;[device-mac-randomization]
# &quot;yes&quot; is already the default for scanning
wifi.scan-rand-mac-address=yes

[connection-mac-randomization]
# Randomize MAC for every ethernet connection
ethernet.cloned-mac-address=random
# Generate a random MAC every time you connect to a wifi network
wifi.cloned-mac-address=random
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unique DUID per connection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/conf.d/duid.conf&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-conf&quot;&gt;[connection]
ipv6.dhcp-duid=stable-uuid
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MAC Address spoofing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section demonstrates how to spoof your Media Access Control (MAC) address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manual MAC randomization with macchanger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find your device interface and check your current MAC address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;# find interface
ip add
sudo iplink show wlp3s0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The address following &lt;code&gt;&quot;link/ether&quot;&lt;/code&gt; is your MAC, bring it down so we can change
it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo ip link set dev wlp3s0 down
# or
# sudo ifconfig wlp3s0 down
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install the &lt;code&gt;macchanger&lt;/code&gt; package and run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo macchanger -a wlp3s0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-a&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;--another&lt;/code&gt;: Set random vendor MAC of the same kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;--random&lt;/code&gt;: Set fully random MAC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically with systemd &amp;amp; macchanger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;systemd unit setting a random address while preserving the original NIC vendor
bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;/etc/systemd/system/macspoof@.service&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-macspoof@.service&quot;&gt;[Unit]
Description=macchanger on %I
Wants=network-pre.target
Before=network-pre.target
BindsTo=sys-subsystem-net-devices-%i.device
After=sys-subsystem-net-devices-%i.device

[Service]
ExecStart=/usr/bin/macchanger -e %I
Type=oneshot

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use &lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt; to randomize everything but it’s important that the vendor
bytes actually match something and aren’t just random numbers so it’s less
recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;@.service&lt;/code&gt; pattern allows per-interface instantiation like
&lt;code&gt;macspoof@wlp3s0.service&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;%I&lt;/code&gt; variable automatically resolves to your interface name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You only need to append your interface name when enabling the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo systemctl enable macspoof@wlp3s0.service
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kicksecure.com/wiki/MAC_Address&quot;&gt;KickSecure MAC_address&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/MAC_address_spoofing&quot;&gt;Arch Wiki MAC address spoofing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tldp.org/LDP/nag2/index.html&quot;&gt;Linux Network Admin Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/NetworkManager&quot;&gt;Arch Wiki NetworkManager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>RethinkDNS</title><id>https://mako088.github.io/android/RethinkDNS_Guide.html</id><updated>2025-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><link href="https://mako088.github.io/android/RethinkDNS_Guide.html" rel="alternate"/><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;RethinkDNS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;!-- toc --&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/rethinkdns.cleaned.png&quot; alt=&quot;RethinkDNS Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not affiliated with RethinkDNS in any way, I’m just a technologist and
privacy advocate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;🔑 Key Terms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand Key Terms &lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP&lt;/strong&gt; (HyperText Transfer Protocol): The standard protocol used by web
browsers and servers to transfer web pages and related resources over the
internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTPS&lt;/strong&gt;: HTTP encrypted using TLS is often referred to as HTTPS.
TLS-encrypted web traffic is by convention exchanged on port 443 by default,
while unencrypted HTTP uses port 80 by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLS&lt;/strong&gt; (Transport Layer Security) is an encryption protocol and is the
standard for enabling two networked applications or devices to exchange
information privately and robustly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mixed content&lt;/strong&gt;: is when an otherwise secure website uses resources fetched
via HTTP or other insecure protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IP&lt;/strong&gt; (Internet Protocol): The address system of the internet that routes
data packets from source to destination devices. IP operates at the network
layer and does not guarantee delivery order or error checking, which is
handled by TCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IP Address&lt;/strong&gt; (Internet Protocol Address): A unique numeric label assigned to
each device on a network, used to identify and locate the device for
communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subnet&lt;/strong&gt; (Subnet Range): represents a block of IP addresses grouped together
under a single rule. Instead of allowing or blocking individual IP addresses
one by one, you define a subnet to include a wide range of IPs within that
block.(Useful for apps that you &lt;code&gt;Isolate&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Host&lt;/strong&gt;: Any device connected to a network with an IP address, capable of
sending and receiving data, including computers, phones, or servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client&lt;/strong&gt;: A device or software (often your computer or phone) that initiates
requests to servers to access resources or services, forming the client-server
model of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port&lt;/strong&gt;: A port in networking is a virtual communication endpoint managed by
a computer’s operating system that helps direct network traffic to specific
apps or services. While an IP address identifies a device on a network, ports
allow the system to know exactly which app or service should handle the
incoming or outgoing data. Web traffic commonly uses port 80 (HTTP) or 443
(HTTPS), so when data arrives for those ports, it’s routed to the web server
application on the device. When we block port 80, we block insecure HTTP
connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TCP&lt;/strong&gt; (Transmission Control Protocol) is responsible for maintaining a
connection through a handshake and putting the packets in the correct order.
TCP will also ask for missing pieces and is known as a reliable but slow
protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UDP&lt;/strong&gt; (User Datagram Protocol) (UDP/IP): is a fast protocol used across the
internet for time-sensitive transmissions such as DNS lookups or VoIP. UDP
allows a computer to send data straight to another without requiring a
handshake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS&lt;/strong&gt; (Domain Name System): stores domain information in a distributed
database and translates domain names into IP addresses and vice versa. This
enables us to only have to remember simple domain names rather than complex IP
addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domain Name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ssd.eff.org
 |   |   |
 |   |  top-level domain
 |   |
 |   second-level domain
 |
subdomain
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;☝️ The hierarchy is read from right to left, the TLD is the highest-level
domain (&lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; here), the second-level domain (&lt;code&gt;eff&lt;/code&gt;) is directly to the left
of the TLD, and anything further left (like &lt;code&gt;ssd&lt;/code&gt;) is a subdomain under that
second-level domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS Server&lt;/strong&gt;: When you search for a domain name (rethinkdns.com) it triggers
a DNS lookup. Several different types of DNS servers typically work together
to complete a single DNS lookup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS Resolver&lt;/strong&gt;: is a server or software component that translates domain
names into IP addresses that devices use to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unicast DNS&lt;/strong&gt;: The traditional DNS setup where each DNS server is assigned a
unique, single IP address. DNS queries from clients are directed to this
specific server regardless of the clients location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anycast DNS&lt;/strong&gt;: Anycast allows a single IP address to be used by multiple
servers. In Anycast DNS, a DNS query can be answered by any one of several DNS
servers, usually the one closest to the user by geographic or network
proximity. This setup reduces latency, increases the availability of DNS
resolution services, and offers protection against DNS flood DDoS attacks by
distributing traffic across multiple servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recursive resolver&lt;/strong&gt; (DNS recursor): is typically the first stop in the
series of the above servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iterative resolver&lt;/strong&gt;: In an iterative DNS query, each DNS server responds
directly to the client with a referral to another server, and the client
continues querying successive servers until it receives the IP address for the
requested domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proxy&lt;/strong&gt;: A proxy, in relation to Orbot with Rethink, is an intermediary
service that routes internet traffic from your device through the Tor network
to provide privacy and anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP(S) Proxy&lt;/strong&gt;: An HTTP proxy is an intermediary server that forwards
HTTP/HTTPS web traffic from a client (e.g., a browser or app) to destination
servers, allowing for privacy, filtering, or routing control while masking the
user’s IP. HTTP proxies only work with web traffic (HTTP/HTTPS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOCKS5&lt;/strong&gt; (Socket Secure 5): Is an internet proxy protocol that transfers
info from one server to another while redirecting the user’s IP address. It
supports both UDP and TCP and can actually improve speed in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pi-hole/pi-hole&quot;&gt;pi-hole&lt;/a&gt;: a DNS sinkhole that protects
your devices content without installing any client-side software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/evilsocket/opensnitch&quot;&gt;OpenSnitch&lt;/a&gt;: is a GNU/Linux
application firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;proxifier&lt;/em&gt;: a proxifier acts as a proxy client, routing specific application
traffic through proxy servers without encrypting data or providing global IP
masking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;VPN&lt;/em&gt; (Virtual Private Network): a VPN creates an encrypted tunnel that routes
all network traffic from your device through a remote server, masking your IP
address and securing your entire connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WireGuard: a modern VPN encryption protocol, its fast and has gained
widespread adoption among VPN providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenVPN: an older, more mature VPN protocol that uses SSL/TLS for encryption.
It’s known for being very reliable and highly configurable but tends to be
slower and more complex than WireGuard. Good VPNs often give you the choice
between protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bypass DNS and Firewall&lt;/code&gt;: Bypass the DNS and Firewall for this app, &lt;strong&gt;this
only works with Rethink’s DNS&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bypass Universal&lt;/code&gt;: Bypass the Universal firewall for this app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt;: The app is excluded from the dns and firewall, Rethink is unaware
of this app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Isolate&lt;/code&gt;: When an app is isolated, only trusted IPs are allowed. (i.e., IPs
or domains you explicitly set trust rules for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🛜(Unmetered Wi-Fi): Wi-Fi settings, either blocked or allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📶 (Metered mobile): Mobile data settings, either blocked or allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#rethinkdns-overview&quot;&gt;RethinkDNS Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bypass DNS and Firewall&lt;/code&gt;: Bypass the DNS and Firewall for this app, &lt;strong&gt;this
only works with Rethink’s DNS&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bypass Universal&lt;/code&gt;: Bypass the Universal firewall for this app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt;: The app is excluded from the dns and firewall, Rethink is unaware
of this app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Isolate&lt;/code&gt;: When an app is isolated, only trusted IPs are allowed. (i.e., IPs
or domains you explicitly set trust rules for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🛜(Unmetered Wi-Fi): Wi-Fi settings, either blocked or allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📶 (Metered mobile): Mobile data settings, either blocked or allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DNS mode routes all DNS traffic generated by all apps to &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; user chosen
DNS-over-HTTPS, DNS-over-TLS, DNSCrypt, or Oblivious DNS-over-HTTPS resolver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firewalls like Rethink that block both UDP and TCP connections are usually
sufficient because nearly all applications rely on these two protocols for their
networking and communication. Almost every app communicates over TCP or UDP, so
blocking these protocols effectively restricts most network traffic from and to
apps, preventing them from connecting without permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will share how I use RethinkDNS, obviously feel free to make changes based on
your threat model and needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different versions of the RethinkDNS have different features and capabilities.
The best version in my opinion is the F-Droid version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://f-droid.org/en/&quot;&gt;F-Droid Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;DNS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to see that GrapheneOS recommends that people use their own
“network provided DNS servers for general purpose usage” (i.e., Your ISPs DNS).
They say that “using the network-provided DNS servers is the best way to blend
in with other users”. Network and web sites can fingerprint and track users
based on non-default DNS configurations.
–&lt;a href=&quot;https://grapheneos.org/faq#default-dns&quot;&gt;grapheneos default-dns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that it is a fact that many ISPs are known to share this data and do other
privacy disrespecting things, I would personally rather make it harder for them.
I included this because they are the experts and the choice is yours, I use a
custom DNS myself. I guess since so many people virtue-signal saying that they
“have nothing to hide”(a reckless, privileged notion) that not many people truly
care about privacy and are likely using the default. The more people that we can
convince to use privacy respecting tools, the better it is for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended Resolvers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand recommended resolvers &lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just the providers I’ve researched personally and not in a specific
order. It’s recommended to regularly test and switch between DNS providers as
location and network conditions play a factor. There are DNS benchmarking tools
available to either download or use in-browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dnsspeedtest.online/&quot;&gt;https://dnsspeedtest.online/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grc.com/dns/benchmark.htm&quot;&gt;https://www.grc.com/dns/benchmark.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quad9&lt;/strong&gt; is known to enforce strong standards in cryptography and was the
first to use DNSSEC cryptographic validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quad9.net/privacy/policy/&quot;&gt;Quad9 privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mullvad DNS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mullvad.net/en/help/privacy-policy&quot;&gt;Mullvad privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NextDNS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nextdns.io/privacy&quot;&gt;NextDNS privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloudflare publishes regular transparency reports and undergoes independent
audits and have a great blog explaining the technology which is a major plus.
GrapheneOS sets Cloudflare as the fallback due to their good privacy policy,
and widespread usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/privacypolicy/&quot;&gt;Cloudflare Privacy Policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RethinkDNS: Their DNS code is open source so anyone can audit it themselves.
They do not collect PII nor seek to profile its users, transparency is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkdns.com/privacy&quot;&gt;DNS Privacy Policy for stub resolvers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fly.io/legal/privacy-policy/&quot;&gt;Fly.io privacy policy for the recursive resolver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/en/dns/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides DNS Recommendations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this article, I’ll be discussing the &lt;strong&gt;RethinkDNS Android App&lt;/strong&gt;.
We’ll later reference the &lt;strong&gt;DNS Blocklist configuring website&lt;/strong&gt;, which is
available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkdns.com/configure&quot;&gt;rethinkdns.com/configure&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❗ NOTE: When you switch to an encrypted DNS resolver, you are shifting your
trust from your ISP’s DNS servers to the third-party DNS provider you choose.
Encryption protects your DNS queries from being seen or intercepted by
outsiders, like your ISP or network eavesdroppers, which improves privacy.
However, the DNS resolver itself still sees all your queries and could
potentially log, analyze, or misuse that data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it’s quite common for ISPs to engage in practices that compromise
user privacy. Do some research, whats their business model, privacy policy, etc.
Unfortunately, with a VPN you are also just shifting the trust. Don’t blindly
choose a VPN either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cyberinsider.com/internet-service-providers-isp-privacy-data-collection/&quot;&gt;ISP data-collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Other DNS&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose the type of resolver you want, I use DNSCrypt. Once you click you can
choose the specific resolver you want such as Quad9. You may notice that it
says &lt;code&gt;Failed: using fallback DNS&lt;/code&gt;. This is only because we haven’t turned it
on yet, we will recheck this once we turn it on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a relay in a specific country, you can click the &lt;code&gt;Relays&lt;/code&gt; tab. For
DNSCrypt you are given the choice between the Netherlands, France, Sweden, Los
Angeles, and Singapore. You might do this if you were trying to circumvent
censorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules&lt;/strong&gt; set the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Advanced DNS filtering (experimental)&lt;/code&gt;: Assign unique IP per DNS request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Prompt on blocklist updates&lt;/code&gt;: This is for if you use Rethink’s custom
blocklists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Prevent DNS leaks&lt;/code&gt;: When enabled, Rethink captures all packets on port 53 and
forwards it to a user-set DNS endpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave all the &lt;code&gt;Advanced&lt;/code&gt; defaults unless you plan on setting up a SOCKS5 proxy,
in which case you will want to enable &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Never proxy DNS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F-Droid Specific:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Split DNS (experimental)&lt;/code&gt;: Forward DNS queries from proxied apps to the
proxy’s DNS servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treat DNS rules as firewall rules (experimental)&lt;/code&gt;: DNS blocking will be
bypassed during resolution; the decision will be made at connection time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set &lt;code&gt;Use fallback DNS as bypass&lt;/code&gt;: where it always uses your fallback DNS for
bypassed apps, domains and IPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also set &lt;code&gt;Use System DNS for undelgated domains&lt;/code&gt; which is generally
safe to enable and useful if access to local network devices or custom
internal domains is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blocklists&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a cool feature, similar to NextDNS if I understand correctly. Since it’s
a system-wide DNS filter it applys to any app that is run through Rethink, not
only your browser, &lt;strong&gt;every app&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blocklists are available when you use Rethink’s DNS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Rethink DNS&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose between &lt;code&gt;Sky&lt;/code&gt; with higher uptime and a stub resolver at cloudflare.com,
OR &lt;code&gt;Max&lt;/code&gt; which is more private and has its recursive resolver at fly.io.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose between the preconfigured blocklists, OR Click &lt;code&gt;RDNS Plus&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;EDIT&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;ADVANCED&lt;/code&gt;, Search blocklists: &lt;code&gt;hagezi&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Multi Pro++ (HaGeZi)&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;APPLY (RDNS PLUS)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can manually Check for an update to the blocklists, which you should
because they are updated regularly with new identified threats. You can also
enable &lt;code&gt;Prompt on blocklist update&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hagezi/dns-blocklists/wiki/FAQ#sources&quot;&gt;hagezi which version should I use?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oisd.nl/&quot;&gt;oisd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F-Droid &amp;amp; Github Versions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When on the F-Droid and GitHub versions of the Rethink, you can download
blocklists from &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; On-device blocklists&lt;/code&gt;, and have them setup
for &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; DNS upstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a known bug where it sometimes when you click &lt;code&gt;DOWNLOAD BLOCKLISTS&lt;/code&gt; it
just keeps listening and never receives anything. The GitHub &lt;code&gt;v05.5n&lt;/code&gt; was
affected by this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;strong&gt;does work&lt;/strong&gt; on the F-Droid version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to use ODoH with the HAGEZI Blocklist you could:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Other DNS&lt;/code&gt;, Choose &lt;code&gt;ODoH&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/code&gt;. Start
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; RULES&lt;/code&gt;, tap &lt;code&gt;On-device blocklists&lt;/code&gt;, and click the
disabled logo, then click &lt;code&gt;DOWNLOAD BLOCKLISTS&lt;/code&gt;. Once the download is complete,
you can select &lt;code&gt;Configure&lt;/code&gt; and select &lt;code&gt;ADVANCED&lt;/code&gt; and search for HAGEZI, choose
MULTI PRO++ and maybe oisd small, then press &lt;code&gt;APPLY (ON-DEVICE)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now any app that doesn’t bypass Rethink will use your chosen blocklists, denying
access to malicious URLs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HAGEZI blocklists are respected for being updated frequently. There are
different levels with MULTI PRO++ (HAGEZI) being the highest and 4 other lest
strict levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Settings explained:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loopback proxy forwarder apps&lt;/strong&gt;: Enable when you want all of your devices
proxy-related traffic to also flow through Rethinks encrypted tunnel. It
ensures apps that proxy DNS/HTTP/SOCKS traffic don’t leak outside the VPN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do not route Private IPs&lt;/strong&gt;: Prevents routing traffic destined for private IP
address ranges (like 192.168.x.x, 10.x.x.x) through the tunnel. Instead, this
traffic goes directly over the local network or system default route. Most
useful when you want devices on your local network (NAS, printers, etc.) to be
reachable by apps on your phone without routing the traffic through Rethinks
tunnel, improving performance and reliability of local connections but
possibly reducing privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loopback (experimental)&lt;/strong&gt;: When enabled, this routes RethinkDNS’s own
internal traffic, such as blocklist downloads, connectivity checks, and DNS
queries made by the app itself, back into the encrypted tunnel through the
loopback device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Setting&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Function&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;When to Use&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Loopback Proxy Forwarder Apps&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Route proxy-forwarder app traffic back into Rethink VPN tunnel&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;When you want consistent VPN/privacy coverage for proxies&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Do Not Route Private IPs&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Avoid routing local network/private IP traffic through VPN (send directly)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;To access local devices without VPN bottlenecks&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Loopback (Experimental)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Route Rethink’s own app traffic (updates/checks) back through VPN tunnel&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;To fully protect app’s own DNS/blocklist traffic&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: The above settings are disabled by default because some are experimental
and can easily break functionality. I have found that the settings below give
the most functionality without breakage 👇️:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Network&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set &lt;code&gt;Use all available networks&lt;/code&gt; to ON. This enables Wifi and mobile data to
be used at the same time by Rethink. (Optional, may use more battery)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set your IP version&lt;/strong&gt;: The default is &lt;code&gt;IPv4&lt;/code&gt;, you can choose between
&lt;code&gt;IPv6 (experimental)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Auto (experimental)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose fallback DNS&lt;/strong&gt;: When your user-preferred DNS is not reachable,
fallback DNS will used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the F-Droid version in &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; ADVANCED&lt;/code&gt;. You can enable
&lt;code&gt;Use fallback DNS as bypass&lt;/code&gt;, which always uses fallback DNS for bypassed
apps, domains, and IPs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally disable &lt;code&gt;Enable network visibility&lt;/code&gt;, just keep in mind that some
apps may break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Shutting this off prevents apps from accessing all available networks,
stopping them from bypassing Rethinks tunnel”. This caused issues with the
browser when turned off.(Some audio/video conference apps like Zoom and Meet
require this)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Firewall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Firewall -&amp;gt; Universal firewall rules&lt;/code&gt; and set the following to ON:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Block all apps when device is locked&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Block when DNS is bypassed&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Block port 80 (insecure HTTP) traffic&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get more restrictive from here, but it will take some manual
intervention to get everything working correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep your firewall rules in mind when you’re configuring per app settings. If
the Universal firewall blocks all apps when the device is locked, do you want
this app affected by this or do you want to let it Bypass the Universal
firewall?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Turn ON DNS and Firewall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt; 🏠:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the big &lt;code&gt;Start&lt;/code&gt; button on the bottom of the screen and leave it set to
the default &lt;code&gt;DNS and Firewall (default)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve started the DNS and Firewall, we can go back to
&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS&lt;/code&gt; and ensure the provider we chose started successfully. You
can also experiment with different types of resolvers, make sure to wait for
below the chosen resolver to say &lt;code&gt;Connected&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, all apps on your device by default allow both Wi-Fi and mobile data access
&lt;strong&gt;through the RethinkDNS encrypted tunnel&lt;/strong&gt;. Try some of your most used Apps to
see if they function correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RethinkDNS’s firewall blocks or restricts any network traffic that isn’t
explicitly allowed. Although by default all apps are allowed network access,
some apps require special permissions or bypasses due to their network behavior.
Many apps rely on multiple external services, backend APIs, etc. that may be
blocked by the firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apps that Don’t work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will use Reddit as an example, the process is the same for any app. Reddit’s
app and website rely on multiple third-party services and external domains
beyond just &lt;code&gt;reddit.com&lt;/code&gt; itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For apps that don’t work it’s important to ensure that your Android systems
&lt;code&gt;Private DNS&lt;/code&gt; is set to &lt;code&gt;Automatic&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Home -&amp;gt; Apps&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for &lt;code&gt;Reddit&lt;/code&gt;, click on it and the Firewall Rules For Reddit will pop up.
Since it is already allowed &lt;code&gt;Unmetered&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Metered&lt;/code&gt; connections and still
doesn’t work, we can try one setting at a time until it does work and this is
the same process for other Apps that aren’t working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you should check your logs and see why it’s being blocked. Look at the
domains involved and set trust rules for said domains. (start by trusting
reddit.com). Check the logs again, add any domains that were blocked related
to reddit. If it is unclear why networking still isn’t working, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bypass Universal&lt;/code&gt;, this allows it to bypass any Universal Firewall rules you
have set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Rethink’s DNS, you can try allowing the app to
&lt;code&gt;Bypass DNS &amp;amp; Firewall&lt;/code&gt;. Try the app again, does it work? If not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also &lt;code&gt;Isolate&lt;/code&gt; an App, you then have to set up &lt;em&gt;trust | allow&lt;/em&gt; rules
for domains or IPs over a period of time which can take a while. You can go to
&lt;code&gt;Apps&lt;/code&gt; and search for the app in question, click on it and at the bottom of
the screen you’ll see &lt;code&gt;IP Logs&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Domain Logs&lt;/code&gt; to help with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt; the app. This makes RethinkDNS completely unaware of the app and is
often what is required for Reddit. It is my understanding that after you
&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt; Reddit for example, your systems Automatic Secure DNS will pick it
up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than watching the logs and setting trust rules over time, you could use
tools like &lt;code&gt;nslookup&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt; to resolve said domain and reveal IP ranges
used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;nslookup reddit.com
Server:         127.0.0.1
Address:        127.0.0.1#53

Non-authoritative answer:
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 151.101.129.140
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 151.101.193.140
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 151.101.1.140
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 151.101.65.140
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 2a04:4e42::396
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 2a04:4e42:600::396
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 2a04:4e42:200::396
Name:   reddit.com
Address: 2a04:4e42:400::396
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolving a domain (like &lt;code&gt;reddit.com&lt;/code&gt;) using tools like &lt;code&gt;nslookup&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt;
reveals multiple IPs because large services use multiple servers across CDNs and
networks for redundancy and performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then run &lt;code&gt;whois&lt;/code&gt; on one of those IPs (e.g., &lt;code&gt;whois 151.101.129.140&lt;/code&gt;) to
identify the subnet ranges owned by Reddit’s CDN provider (Fastly in this case),
which helps when setting up subnet range allow rules in Rethink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand `whois` Example Output &lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;whois 151.101.129.140

#
# ARIN WHOIS data and services are subject to the Terms of Use
# available at: https://www.arin.net/resources/registry/whois/tou/
#
# If you see inaccuracies in the results, please report at
# https://www.arin.net/resources/registry/whois/inaccuracy_reporting/
#
# Copyright 1997-2025, American Registry for Internet Numbers, Ltd.
#


NetRange:       151.101.0.0 - 151.101.255.255
CIDR:           151.101.0.0/16
NetName:        SKYCA-3
NetHandle:      NET-151-101-0-0-1
Parent:         RIPE-ERX-151 (NET-151-0-0-0-0)
NetType:        Direct Allocation
OriginAS:
Organization:   Fastly, Inc. (SKYCA-3)
RegDate:        2016-02-01
Updated:        2021-12-14
Ref:            https://rdap.arin.net/registry/ip/151.101.0.0


OrgName:        Fastly, Inc.
OrgId:          SKYCA-3
Address:        PO Box 78266
City:           San Francisco
StateProv:      CA
PostalCode:     94107
Country:        US
RegDate:        2011-09-16
Updated:        2025-03-25
Ref:            https://rdap.arin.net/registry/entity/SKYCA-3


OrgNOCHandle: FNO19-ARIN
OrgNOCName:   Fastly Network Operations
OrgNOCPhone:  +1-415-404-9374
OrgNOCEmail:  noc@fastly.com
OrgNOCRef:    https://rdap.arin.net/registry/entity/FNO19-ARIN

OrgTechHandle: FRA19-ARIN
OrgTechName:   Fastly RIR Administrator
OrgTechPhone:  +1-415-518-9103
OrgTechEmail:  rir-admin@fastly.com
OrgTechRef:    https://rdap.arin.net/registry/entity/FRA19-ARIN

OrgAbuseHandle: ABUSE4771-ARIN
OrgAbuseName:   Abuse Account
OrgAbusePhone:  +1-415-496-9353
OrgAbuseEmail:  abuse@fastly.com
OrgAbuseRef:    https://rdap.arin.net/registry/entity/ABUSE4771-ARIN


#
# ARIN WHOIS data and services are subject to the Terms of Use
# available at: https://www.arin.net/resources/registry/whois/tou/
#
# If you see inaccuracies in the results, please report at
# https://www.arin.net/resources/registry/whois/inaccuracy_reporting/
#
# Copyright 1997-2025, American Registry for Internet Numbers, Ltd.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⚠️ Use caution when setting trust rules for subnet ranges, as this grants
access to all services hosted within that range, potentially including
services unrelated to the one you intend to access. Best practice is to first
attempt to trust the specific domain name (e.g., reddit.com), which is
generally the most granular and secure method. Only consider trusting broader
subnet ranges (like 151.101.0.0/16) as a last resort if domain-based rules
fail to resolve connectivity issues for the intended service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The subnet range for that IP: &lt;code&gt;151.101.0.0 - 151.101.255.255&lt;/code&gt; (CIDR notation:
&lt;code&gt;151.101.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as a starting point to get Reddit working we could trust the following subnet
range:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPv4: &lt;code&gt;151.101.0.0/16&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This subnet covers the full range from &lt;code&gt;151.101.0.0&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;151.101.255.255&lt;/code&gt;,
which includes all related IPs Reddit uses via Fastly’s CDN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owning organization: &lt;code&gt;Fastly, Inc.&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; More…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Firefox Encrypted DNS through Rethink&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, make sure you can visit a few sites in Firefox. If you can, then your
browser traffic should be routed through the Rethink tunnel, we will check here.
If you can’t, go to &lt;code&gt;Home -&amp;gt; Apps&lt;/code&gt; and search for Firefox, is networking
enabled?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RethinkDNS Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the best experience routing your browser traffic through your custom
endpoint (e.g., DNSCrypt) on both Wi-Fi and mobile data ensure the following are
set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not turn on &lt;code&gt;Block any app not in use&lt;/code&gt; in the Universal firewall. After
some Log digging, I found that this causes the browser to fail more often than
not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Network -&amp;gt; Enable network visibility&lt;/code&gt; set to ON. I had
experimented with turning this off and certain websites wouldn’t load when on
Wi-Fi and none would load on mobile data. Turning it back on seemed to fix
both with no leaks detected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Double check that in Rethink’s &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Prevent DNS leaks&lt;/code&gt; is ON, as
well as the Universal Firewalls &lt;code&gt;Block when DNS is bypassed&lt;/code&gt; ON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firefox Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Firefox, plug &lt;code&gt;about:config&lt;/code&gt; into the URL bar and scroll down to
&lt;code&gt;network.trr.mode&lt;/code&gt; and change its value to &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; to prevent leaking DNS queries
to the System resolver. Also in &lt;code&gt;about:config&lt;/code&gt; scroll down to
&lt;code&gt;media.peerconnection.enabled&lt;/code&gt;, double-click to set it to false to prevent
WebRTC leaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IronFox no longer lets you adjust the &lt;code&gt;network.trr.mode&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;about:config&lt;/code&gt;, you
adjust the &lt;code&gt;trr.mode&lt;/code&gt; through the DNS over HTTPS settings. Set it to
&lt;code&gt;Default Protection&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;OFF&lt;/code&gt; and check for dns leaks. Fennec also has issues
with setting &lt;code&gt;network.trr.mode 3&lt;/code&gt; and falls back to insecure methods. I would
suggest using the built in DNS over HTTPS for Fennec on max protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The trade-off is that disabling WebRTC also disables any websites or apps
using WebRTC for real-time communication (like video calls or chat functions)
from working correctly.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebRTC&quot;&gt;Wikipedia WebRTC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Firefox &lt;code&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Privacy &amp;amp; Security&lt;/code&gt;, set &lt;code&gt;DNS over HTTPS&lt;/code&gt; to
&lt;code&gt;Default Protection&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;OFF&lt;/code&gt;, this enables Firefox to use RethinkDNS’s DNSCrypt
resolver or whatever you chose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checking for DNS Leaks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;https://dnsleaktest.com
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also crosscheck with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;https://ipleak.net
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ipleak.net&lt;/code&gt; may show many more servers but as long as they are all related to
your resolver (i.e., WoodyNet for Quad9) you are not leaking to your ISP or
other third-parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For DNSCrypt with Quad9 Security, &lt;code&gt;dnsleaktest&lt;/code&gt; found 5 servers all with the ISP
&lt;code&gt;WoodyNet&lt;/code&gt; indicating success through Quad9. Quad9 relies on Packet Clearing
House, that’s where the &lt;code&gt;WoodyNet&lt;/code&gt; name comes from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When on mobile data, when going to &lt;code&gt;https://dnsleaktest.com&lt;/code&gt; the results may
show more servers. As long as they are all the same ISP you’re good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A different solution could be to experiment with more strict RethinkDNS settings
and just use the browsers built-in DNS over HTTPS on max protection. Having more
strict defaults for Rethink with all of your apps and configuring your browser
separate may be a better option, the choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When hunting down a solution you can go to &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Logs&lt;/code&gt;, then try to
visit the site that wouldn’t work while watching the logs. You should see
&lt;code&gt;Firefox&lt;/code&gt; pop up, click it, in the top right of the pop up should be the reason
it was blocked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://privacytests.org/&quot;&gt;PrivacyTests.org&lt;/a&gt;, tests different browsers in
different privacy categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#duckduckgo&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also tested DuckDuckGo with its stock configuration and &lt;code&gt;dnsleaktest.com&lt;/code&gt;
showed that DDGs traffic was successfully tunneled through Rethink to Quad9s’
servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;dnsleaktest.com&lt;/code&gt; showed all &lt;code&gt;WoodyNet&lt;/code&gt; ISPs indicating success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chromium-based-browsers-brave&quot;&gt;Chromium Based Browsers (Brave)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Brave, if you want your DNS routed through Rethink you have to turn
&lt;code&gt;Use secure DNS&lt;/code&gt; off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had to set Brave to &lt;em&gt;Bypass Universal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: Brave has been known to have some spyware in the past, though most of it
can be opted out of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#more-fine-grained-control--enhanced-privacy&quot;&gt;More Fine Grained Control &amp;amp; Enhanced Privacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section we will switch from a default allow to a default deny; blocking
network access to every app. We will then go through and only enable networking
for the apps that we need and trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand Android Privacy Tips for the paranoid &lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the idea of someone forcing you to unlock your phone so they
can sift through your data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s often recommended to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; use biometrics as they can be forcibly be
taken from you while a password typically can’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cellebrite&quot;&gt;Cellebrite&lt;/a&gt; relies on your phone
being in AFU mode which is After first unlock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BFU&lt;/strong&gt;: Before First Unlock. This refers to the state right after a device
restarts. Since you haven’t entered your password yet, the system has not
unlocked the phone’s storage, so its contents remain encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AFU&lt;/strong&gt;: After First Unlock. In this state, the device has been unlocked at
least once since it was powered on, even if it is currently locked. The
encryption keys are loaded into RAM, making the device’s stored data more
accessible and increasing the potential attack surface compared to the BFU
state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set the Auto optimization (Auto Restart) to the shortest amount of time
possible. When your phone first reboots it is in BFU mode which is Before
first unlock mode. Biometrics are usually disabled in this mode and the
encryption keys are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; saved in RAM making the attack surface much
smaller.(i.e., they typically have to guess the password or brute-force it)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That said, if someone gets your phone while it’s in AFU mode they will only
have the amount of time until your next auto reboot to try to extract your
data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also try to reduce the number of unlock attempts before the device
wipes. The default is typically 20 attempts, I haven’t found a way to lower
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t really trust Airplane mode on anything but GrapheneOS. If you are
able to remove your battery, do that when it matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your &lt;code&gt;About phone&lt;/code&gt; section, name your device something that doesn’t expose
anything useful about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set a pin for your phones sim card to prevent sim swaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider something like mint mobile or visible, they often let you register
with only a spoofed email address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bluetooth is inherently insecure and broadcasts information about your device
constantly. Walmart and other stores have started using Bluetooth to see hot
zones to strategically place adds on the most traveled areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edgescan.com/bluetooth-and-the-invisible-security-threat-youre-probably-not-listening-to/&quot;&gt;Bluetooth the invisible threat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexvakulov/2025/02/20/11-types-of-bluetooth-attacks-and-how-to-protect-your-devices/&quot;&gt;Types of bluetooth attacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn off Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, Location, Nearby device scanning, etc. when not in
use or needed. Your weather app doesn’t need your location 24/7, find one that
lets you manually enter your location and time zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a password manager rather than using the one built into the browser, I
like BitWarden for sync and KeepassDX for self storage. Since you don’t have
to remember the passwords, have it generate long complex unique passwords for
each app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use KeepassDX to store a complex password for Bitwarden that is kept
100% offline so your synced passwords are better protected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Google&lt;/code&gt; in
&lt;code&gt;Google services -&amp;gt; All services -&amp;gt; Privacy &amp;amp; security&lt;/code&gt; Select &lt;code&gt;Ads&lt;/code&gt; and either
Reset advertising ID every so often, or Delete advertising ID but know the
consequences of the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same &lt;code&gt;All services&lt;/code&gt; area, click &lt;code&gt;Usage &amp;amp; diagnostics&lt;/code&gt; to disable it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn off &lt;code&gt;Improve Location Accuracy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to your accounts &lt;code&gt;Manage your Google Account&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Data &amp;amp; privacy&lt;/code&gt; and disable
all the Activity tracking (Pause it or turn it off).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you rely on Google services, in the &lt;code&gt;Data &amp;amp; privacy&lt;/code&gt; section, it is helpful
to run a &lt;code&gt;Privacy Checkup&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re done, always go to &lt;code&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Accounts and backup&lt;/code&gt; and remove the
Google account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommended that you &lt;strong&gt;remove Android System SafetyCore&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.protectstar.com/en/blog/android-system-safetycore-hidden-installation-and-what-you-should-know&quot;&gt;What is SafetyCore and why you should delete it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaspersky.com.au/blog/what-are-android-safetycore-and-key-verifier/34736/&quot;&gt;Google forcing Android System SafetyCore on users to scan for nudes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F-Droid&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F-Droid is a free and open-source app store for Android that only distributes
open-source software, without ads, proprietary code, or user tracking. All apps
are vetted for privacy and transparency, making it a strong alternative to
Google Play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No registration or account is required, further protecting privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google restricts apps that remove Google services or modify their core features
to disable their data collection strategies. This is why you won’t find many
privacy by default browsers in Google Play. Browsers like IronFox and Cromite
are solid options that disable telemetry and more that are available outside of
the Play ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use IronFox as my default and have been happy with it so far. It
comes with uBlock installed by default which I recommend that you learn how to
get the most out of. With Firefox fingerprint protection, a few about:config
tweaks, and uBlock you can accomplish what used to take 6 extensions to do. See:
&lt;a href=&quot;#ublock-origin&quot;&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more compartmentalization, Brave Browser now has an F-Droid repository that
can be added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open F-Droid, in Settings click Repositories, click +, and for the Brave
official repository add the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: If you don’t want to add a repo, you can use the FFUpdater app to
install privacy friendly browsers including brave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;https://brave-browser-apk-release.s3.brave.com/fdroid/repo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you can visit
&lt;a href=&quot;https://brave-browser-apk-release.s3.brave.com/fdroid/repo/index.html&quot;&gt;https://brave-browser-apk-release.s3.brave.com/fdroid/repo/index.html&lt;/a&gt; and scan
the QR code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another app that I recently discovered on F-Droid is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://f-droid.org/en/packages/de.marmaro.krt.ffupdater/&quot;&gt;FFUpdater&lt;/a&gt; app. It
enables you to install and update different privacy friendly browsers as well as
updating FairEmail, K-9 Mail/Thunderbird, and Orbot in a privacy respecting way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FairEmail is great, it has many privacy features including support for
encryption,reformatting messages to prevent phishing, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install apps through FFUpdater tap the phone logo with the down arrow on
the top right of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aurora Store is an open-source client for Google Play that respects user privacy
and lets you download and update proprietary apps with an anonymous account. You
can use F-Droid for open-source apps and Aurora for proprietary apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would recommend against Obtainium, the dev is a piece of shit and you can do
anything it can do easily without it. Discoverium is a fork run by someone else,
might be an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option I came across that I haven’t tried yet is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zapstore.dev/&quot;&gt;Zapstore&lt;/a&gt; It’s a decentralized, permissionless app store
that lets you support devs without PII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2019/01/stop-tracking-my-emails&quot;&gt;EFF stop-tracking-my-emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share Files and more anonymously&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://onionshare.org/&quot;&gt;OnionShare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharing Images&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clean metadata before sharing pics, I personally use
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Crazy-Marvin/MetadataRemover&quot;&gt;Metadata Remover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SearXNG&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we’re on the topic of browsers, it’s worth considering a privacy-focused
metasearch engine like SearXNG. SearXNG anonymizes your search queries and
removes any identifying data before passing them along to Google or other search
engines. This way, you can receive top-quality search results while keeping your
privacy intact&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started find a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://searx.space/&quot;&gt;local instances&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://searx.neocities.org/nojs.html&quot;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt; and either bookmark them for
quick access or do what I do and add them to use as your default search engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Firefox go to &lt;code&gt;about:preferences#search&lt;/code&gt;, scroll to the bottom and click
&lt;code&gt;Add&lt;/code&gt;. Name it whatever you want and for the URL add one of the local instances
followed by &lt;code&gt;search?q=%s&lt;/code&gt; for example, for an instance in the US with A+
ratings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;https://searx.ankha.ac/search?q=%s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then click &lt;code&gt;Add Engine&lt;/code&gt;, and back near the top of the page you can set one
instance as your default search engine and another for private windows. I have
had a good experience so far using SearXNG with the occasional problem that is
solved by using a different instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❗️ Note: When using a public SearXNG instance from someone you don’t know, you
are trusting the operator since they can see the IP address making the
searches and might keep logs. The site https://searx.space/ provides helpful
details to choose instances based on trust and location. If you want the
highest level of privacy and full control, running your own instance is the
best option—though it requires more setup. Using public instances is a great
way to get started and improve privacy compared to regular search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browser compartmentalization&lt;/strong&gt; is a technique where you use multiple browsers
to separate different types of online activities. Instead of doing all browsing
in a single browser, you dedicate specific browsers to distinct tasks, for
example, one browser for email and banking, another for social media, and a
third for casual web surfing. This separation makes it difficult for websites
and trackers to link your activities across different contexts because cookies,
trackers, and browsing data are isolated within each browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI and social media Apps often require extensive permissions and deep access
to your device data and can run background processes that you can’t easily
monitor. If you avoid the apps and only access AI and social media in your
browser you get the benefits of browser sandboxing, tracking prevention,
cookie controls and more. You gain more benefits by using the
compartmentalization technique explained above, possibly one for AI and one
for social media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following website lists the tracking protection mechanisms implemented by
the major browsers and browser engines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cookiestatus.com/&quot;&gt;Cookie Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; ✔️ Click to Expand uBlock Guide &lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkenfox and Betterfox are JavaScript configuration files used to harden/control
Firefox settings on a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yokoffing/BetterFox?tab=readme-ov-file&quot;&gt;BetterFox&lt;/a&gt; does a
great job explaining how to use uBlock with solid recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yokoffing/filterlists?tab=readme-ov-file#guidelines&quot;&gt;BetterFox uBlock filterlists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to apply the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yokoffing/filterlists/blob/main/privacy_essentials.txt&quot;&gt;Privacy Essentials&lt;/a&gt;
list you would click
&lt;a href=&quot;https://subscribe.adblockplus.org/?location=https://raw.githubusercontent.com/yokoffing/filterlists/main/privacy_essentials.txt&amp;amp;title=Privacy%20Essentials&quot;&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt;,
which launches the uBlock asset viewer where you can see all of the domains that
will be blocked before clicking &lt;code&gt;Subscribe&lt;/code&gt; again to apply them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding other lists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hagezi/dns-blocklists&quot;&gt;Hagezi dns-blocklists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ppfeufer/adguard-filter-list&quot;&gt;adguard-filter-list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the uBlock logo, Settings, Filter lists, scroll to the bottom and choose
Import…, Paste the url of your chosen list, and click Apply changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/arkenfox/user.js/&quot;&gt;Arkenfox&lt;/a&gt; suggests adding
the Actually Legitimate URL Shortener Tool. Add
&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DandelionSprout/adfilt/master/LegitimateURLShortener.txt&quot;&gt;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DandelionSprout/adfilt/master/LegitimateURLShortener.txt&lt;/a&gt;
to the Import… section and click Apply changes. If you scroll up, you’ll see
that it was added and chosen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setup your &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki/Blocking-mode&quot;&gt;Blocking mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many opt for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki/Blocking-mode:-medium-mode&quot;&gt;medium mode&lt;/a&gt;.
To do so you need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Settings pane&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the dashboard, and choose I am an advanced user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filter lists pane&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of uBO’s filter lists: checked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EasyList: checked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Lowe’s Ad server list: checked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EasyPrivacy: checked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online Malicious URL Blocklist: checked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My rules pane (4th pane from the left)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underneath Temporary rules add, you literally type this in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;* * 3p-script block&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;* * 3p-frame block&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Save&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;- Commit&lt;/code&gt; (Not required on phone)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting medium mode on your phone is likely overkill because it’s not super
quick to switch broken sites to easy mode as it is on a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fallback to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki/Blocking-mode:-easy-mode&quot;&gt;easy mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the uBlock logo while on the site you want to use easy mode on. You’ll see
the power button to the top right, the Global rules and the Local rules which
start 3 boxes from the left. Click the box under the Local rules for 3rd-party
scripts. The box will change colors, dark gray = NOOP (No Operation). This tells
uBO to ignore the aggressive global block for this site, and let the normal
filter lists handle the blocking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the padlock to make the rules NOOP rules permanent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also disable JavaScript in Settings as needed replacing the need for
NoScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki&quot;&gt;uBlock Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/09/f-droid-calls-for-regulators-to-stop-googles-crackdown-on-sideloading/&quot;&gt;Ars Technica F-Droid &amp;amp; sideloading restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://f-droid.org/en/2025/09/29/google-developer-registration-decree.html&quot;&gt;F-Droid and Google’s Developer Registration Decree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Default Deny&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read the following GrapheneOS discussion forum written by an RDNS dev:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://discuss.grapheneos.org/d/12728-proton-apps-pinging-google-api-sending-reports-back-after-opting-out/54&quot;&gt;GrapheneOS Discussion Forum on Rethink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post suggests you go to &lt;code&gt;Home -&amp;gt; Apps&lt;/code&gt; and right under &lt;code&gt;Showing all apps&lt;/code&gt;
click on the grayed out 🛜📶 to set a rule to &lt;strong&gt;block both Metered and Unmetered
connections to all apps by default&lt;/strong&gt;. This will block both Wi-Fi and mobile data
connections to &lt;strong&gt;all apps&lt;/strong&gt; on your device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point here is that not every App on your device needs network access all the
time or at all in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for the apps you use/trust and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;start by enabling Wi-Fi 🛜 and mobile-data 📶 as well as Bypass Universal so
your required apps aren’t blocked right when the screen shuts off or affected
by the firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, check your logs and see why it’s being blocked. Look at the domains
involved and set trust rules for said domains. If it is unclear why networking
still isn’t working, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Rethink’s DNS, you can try allowing the app to
&lt;code&gt;Bypass DNS &amp;amp; Firewall&lt;/code&gt;. Try the app again, does it work? If not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also &lt;code&gt;Isolate&lt;/code&gt; an App, you then have to set up &lt;em&gt;trust | allow&lt;/em&gt; rules
for domains or IPs over a period of time which can take a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt; the app. This makes RethinkDNS completely unaware of the app and is
often what is required for Reddit. It is my understanding that after you
&lt;code&gt;Exclude&lt;/code&gt; an App, your systems Automatic Secure DNS will pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few apps that typically need network access on Android:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Play services (&lt;code&gt;com.google.android.gms&lt;/code&gt;): push notifications, safety
checks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Play Store (&lt;code&gt;com.android.vending&lt;/code&gt;) app updates and downloads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android System (usually UID 1000, often &lt;code&gt;android&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;system&lt;/code&gt;): Core OS
connectivity checks, NTP time sync, and network management. Blocking can cause
“no internet” errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android System WebView (&lt;code&gt;com.google.android.webview&lt;/code&gt;): Renders web contents in
apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download Manager (&lt;code&gt;com.android.providers.downloads&lt;/code&gt;): Manages file downloads
from apps/browser. Without it, downloads stall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media Storage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Settings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tor&quot;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tor itself is a network and software that anonymizes traffic by encrypting it
and bouncing it though a series of volunteer-operated relays around the world
before reaching the destination. Orbot uses this Tor network to encrypt and
anonymize internet traffic for Android apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orbot routes app traffic through Tor but doesn’t provide the same kind of
traffic isolation and sandboxing that Tor browser offers on desktop. Be aware of
the limitations and use Tor Browser on a hardened system or specialized software
such as Tails or Whonix when anonymity truly matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn how Tor works, I suggest reading the following in this
order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/04/30/in-praise-of-tor/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides In Praise of Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/en/advanced/tor-overview/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides Tor Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ssd.eff.org/module/how-to-use-tor&quot;&gt;EFF How to: Use Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tor is at risk, and needs our help&lt;/strong&gt;. Despite its strength and history, Tor
isn’t safe from the same attacks oppressive regimes and misinformed legislators
direct at encryption and many other privacy-enhancing
technologies.–&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/04/30/in-praise-of-tor/#how-to-support-tor&quot;&gt;How to Support Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;
✔️ Click to Expand Tor Section
&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❗️ WARNING: Tor gets much of its funding from the US government and is not
immune to vulnerabilities or misconfigurations.Tor Browser is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the most
secure browser, anonymity and security can often be at odds with each other.
Having the exact same browser as many other people isn’t the best security
practice, but it is great for anonymity. Tor is also based on Firefox Esr,
which only receives patches for vulnerabilities considered Critical or High
which can be taken advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tor Project has also done some sketchy/questionable things lately such as
removing user agent spoofing which made every user appear as if they were using
the same version of Windows. This decision reduces anonymity and is questionable
at best, seems to me there ought to be a very good reason for doing this which I
can’t find. Tor is still one of the best anonymity solutions, just stay informed
and cautious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is a summary of some of the Tor Overview, all credit goes to them.
It is important to spread the word when you can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are fortunate to live outside of oppressive regimes with extreme
censorship, using Tor for every day, mundane activities is likely safe and won’t
put you on any harmful “list.” Even if it did, you’d be in good company, these
lists mostly contain great people working tirelessly to defend human rights and
online privacy worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using Tor regularly for ordinary browsing, you help strengthen the network,
making it more robust and anonymous for everyone. This collective support makes
staying private easier for activists, journalists, and anyone facing online
surveillance or censorship. The writer of the PrivacyGuides article mentions
using Tor when he needs to access Google Maps to protect his privacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, consider embracing Tor not only for sensitive browsing but also for daily
routine tasks. Every user adds valuable noise to the network, helping protect
privacy and freedom for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#setting-up-orbot-with-a-tcp-only-proxy&quot;&gt;Setting up Orbot with a TCP-only Proxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/orbot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Orbot Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helpful guide, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecyberexpress.com/what-is-orbot/&quot;&gt;What is Orbot?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCP-Only Proxies forward all TCP-level connections from selected apps to Orbot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCP-Only Proxies work best for Apps that use multiple TCP protocols beyond just
basic web browsing (HTTP/HTTPS) like messaging apps (Signal), search apps (DDG),
etc. Because it proxies all TCP traffic, it can cause some apps to slow down or
break if they expect direct DNS or UDP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First install Orbot, Open &lt;code&gt;Orbot -&amp;gt; More -&amp;gt; Orbot Settings&lt;/code&gt; and turn on
&lt;code&gt;Power User Mode&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;This is important&lt;/strong&gt;, if you forget this Rethinks auto Orbot
will not let you choose between SOCKS and HTTP proxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should also check &lt;code&gt;Allow Background Starts&lt;/code&gt; ON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup Orbot&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Add / Remove 0 apps&lt;/code&gt;, search for an app that you want to run through
Orbot. For simple testing I chose DuckDuckGo with a TCP-only Proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Home -&amp;gt; Apps&lt;/code&gt; search for &lt;code&gt;Orbot&lt;/code&gt; and set &lt;code&gt;Orbot -&amp;gt; Bypass Universal&lt;/code&gt; ON&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first time starting Orbot through Rethink, you’ll have to click the
&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup Orbot -&amp;gt; Orbot&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;Connect&lt;/code&gt; as well as grant
initial permissions. After you start Orbot successfully, check out Rethinks
&lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt; and below the STOP button should say &lt;code&gt;Protected With Tor&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open DuckDuckGo and go to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;https://dnsleaktest.com
# CrossCheck
https://ipcheck.net
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;❗ You may see that ipleaktest initially shows a Tor exit relay location such
as the Netherlands, once you complete a Standard Test, it still shows WoodyNet
ISPs. Since I configured Rethink to use DNSCrypt with Quad9 this is completely
expected. This confirms that my DNS traffic is not leaking to my ISP and is
properly anonymized through Tor and Quad9. As long as you don’t see your
actual ISP’s servers in the results, your setup is working as intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can add more apps that would benefit from anonymity such as FairEmail,
RSS feeds, and crypto wallets. I believe for Signal, it requires that you to set
up the SOCKS5 proxy to work correctly which is pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look into an RSS Feed, they give you complete control of the content you
consume, no algorithm involved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can also be useful on public Wi-Fi or other insecure networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also open Orbot and &lt;code&gt;Choose How to Connect&lt;/code&gt;, if you want to hide Tor
use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you live in an area where Tor use isn’t discriminated against, consider
Activating your Orbot &lt;code&gt;Kindness&lt;/code&gt; tab so others that are in oppressive regimes
can use your device as a bridge. This is a great way to give back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#setting-up-a-socks5-proxy&quot;&gt;Setting up a SOCKS5 Proxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have Orbot set up through auto mode, you’ll have to disable it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open &lt;code&gt;Orbot -&amp;gt; More&lt;/code&gt;: Near the bottom of the screen you’ll see &lt;code&gt;HTTP: 8118&lt;/code&gt;, and
&lt;code&gt;SOCKS: 9050&lt;/code&gt;, these are the Port numbers. We will compare these to Rethinks
defaults. (They match).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Rethink, &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup SOCKS5 Proxy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the App dropdown choose &lt;code&gt;Orbot&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hostname: &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Port Number: &lt;code&gt;9050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave the rest of the defaults and Hit &lt;code&gt;Set&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;, below the STOP button you should see &lt;code&gt;Protected With SOCKS Proxy&lt;/code&gt;.
Now all of your devices traffic that doesn’t bypass Rethink is routed through
the SOCKS5 proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS&lt;/code&gt; and turn &lt;code&gt;Never proxy DNS&lt;/code&gt; ON&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open your browser and visit &lt;code&gt;https://dnsleaktest.com&lt;/code&gt;, your public IP should
no longer be your ISPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOCKS5 alone doesn’t encrypt the traffic; it only proxies or routes it. Orbot
uses SOCKS5 to let apps route traffic into the Tor network. Once inside the
Tor network, the traffic is encrypted in layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a misconception that Orbot is a “free VPN”. It’s actually part of an
anonymity network designed to hide your identity by sending your traffic
through multiple servers. And the SOCKS5 proxy that Orbot uses isn’t a VPN
either, it simply directs certain app traffic through a proxy server without
creating a full encrypted tunnel from your device like a VPN does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;WireGuard/VPN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep your goals in mind before paying for a VPN, some allow you to pay with cash
anonymously such as Mullvad VPN and a few others. Remember that you are
transferring trust, from your ISP to the VPN provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup WireGuard -&amp;gt; +&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the WireGuard protocol, the provider usually gives you either a QR Code, or
a configuration file (e.g., &lt;code&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt; file) which is a plaintext file that
contains what is needed. You download that file and Click &lt;code&gt;IMPORT&lt;/code&gt; which brings
up your phones filesystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, the &lt;code&gt;CREATE&lt;/code&gt; option for advanced users who are setting up their
own WireGuard network, typically if you host your own VPN server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this is setup you should always verify that your traffic is encrypted
(hidden IP) and your DNS queries are protected (no leaks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First check what your IP address is before enabling WireGuard at
&lt;code&gt;whatismyipaddress.com&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ipleak.net&lt;/code&gt;, take note of your Public IP, ISP,
and City/Country this is your real info that the VPN needs to hide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connect to your Wireguard/VPN server. Choose the server location you want and
go back to check again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check for leaks, go to &lt;code&gt;dnsleaktest.com&lt;/code&gt; and run a Standard test. If you
don’t see your Public IP listed anywhere, you don’t have a leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixing DNS Leaks&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use WireGuard in Simple mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, use &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; DNS -&amp;gt; Split DNS&lt;/code&gt; with WireGuard in
&lt;code&gt;Advanved + Lockdown&lt;/code&gt; mode (if running on Android 12+)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure your DNS requests go through your VPN, check
&lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Logs -&amp;gt; DNS&lt;/code&gt;. Tap on the entries that appear there, which should
bring up a bottomsheet with more info about the request and how it was handled.
Requests handled by WireGuard are shown with sub-text “resolved x min ago by
wg…” –celzero&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proton VPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works for ProtonVPN Free as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written by celzero
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/rethinkdns/comments/163e83l/proton_vpn/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your Android, visit https://account.protonvpn.com/downloads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scroll to WireGuard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give it a name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select Android&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enable VPN options as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press Create or tap on Download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Rethink, goto Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup WireGuard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tap on the “+” button&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose Import&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select the downloaded configuration file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the import is successful, you should see a new profile prefixed wg added
to the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tap on that &lt;code&gt;wg&lt;/code&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new screen that opens up, tap on Add / Remove applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select apps that should be part of this particular WireGuard profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable / disable that wg profile as desirable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On my phone, when I saved the VPN profile, it automatically added &lt;code&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt; to
the end of the file causing the import to fail. I was able to open my phones
documents and long hold the file to rename it, afterwards I was able import
it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SIMPLE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you enable: &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup WireGuard - SIMPLE&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All connections from all apps, including DNS, will be routed to a single, active
WireGuard VPN. Other active WireGuard VPNs, if any, will be stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you tap SIMPLE, you can see the name of your VPN, check your Logs, and see
your Peer connection.(your device that participates in the VPN network)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADVANCED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same as above but tap &lt;code&gt;ADVANCED&lt;/code&gt; before enabling the toggle. This lets you
choose which apps will be routed through the VPN while the rest are routed as
usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Mode also lets you enable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lockdown&lt;/strong&gt;: Selected apps will only be routed through this WireGuard VPN,
regardless of whether the VPN is active or disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always-on&lt;/strong&gt;: All connections and apps not routed by other WireGuard VPNs
will be routed by this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile only&lt;/strong&gt;: Use this WireGuard exclusively over mobile data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you configure your Advanced settings as needed, enable the toggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always make sure to watch your Logs as well as test with something like
&amp;lt;dnsleaktest.com&amp;gt;, you shouldn’t see your actual Public IP anywhere. It’s
advisable to check for WebRTC Leaks as well if you have that enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Troubleshooting VPN issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few Proxy settings in &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Network -&amp;gt; PROXY&lt;/code&gt;, where you
can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enable &lt;code&gt;Do not randomize WireGuard listen port&lt;/code&gt;: Keep WireGuard listen ports
fixed (no randomization) in Advanced mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enable &lt;code&gt;Endpoint-Independent mapping&lt;/code&gt;: When enabled, UDP sockets maintain a
fixed address and port for all destinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check your Logs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Proxy -&amp;gt; Setup WireGuard&lt;/code&gt;, click on your VPN which will give
you access to the &lt;code&gt;LOGS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the top entry, it will bring up the IP address and domain and show your
rules the app. You can click the dropdown menu’s to set new Universal Firewall
rules, as well as block/trust rules for IPs and domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#logs&quot;&gt;Logs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On-device logging is on by default. You can find it in &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Settings&lt;/code&gt;.
From there, you can set the log level and choose a notification action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone else uses your phone, it’s probably a good idea to enable app lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;code&gt;Configure -&amp;gt; Logs&lt;/code&gt;, and try to access the app that’s not working. You
should see said app at the top of the Network Logs, click it. In the top right
of the tab, you’ll see the reason why it’s not working such as: &lt;code&gt;App Blocked&lt;/code&gt;,
or &lt;code&gt;DNS Bypass&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;code&gt;DNS Bypass&lt;/code&gt; means that the App in question is trying to bypass the Rethink
Tunnel and being actively blocked. You can search for said app and try setting
IP or Port Trust rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also go to &lt;code&gt;Home -&amp;gt; Apps&lt;/code&gt; and search for the App you need, click on it
and at the bottom of the screen you will see &lt;code&gt;IP Logs&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Domain Logs&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you click on the log of the app in question, you’ll be given 3 drop down
options. If you set an app to Bypass DNS and Firewall settings, you will see
that in the first dropdown box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next drop down is &lt;code&gt;Block,trust this IP for this app&lt;/code&gt; where you can set a
rule to &lt;code&gt;Block&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Trust&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;
✔️ Click to Expand Resources
&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things change frequently in the privacy/security relm, many sites provide an RSS
feed that automatically updates when they post new content. I’ve listed a few
feeds that are good to follow IMO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS&lt;/strong&gt; (Really Simple Syndication) is a technology that delivers automatic
updates from your favorite websites, blogs, or podcasts in a standardized
format. It saves you time by eliminating the need to manually check for new
content. Best of all, your feed includes only what you choose—no algorithms
deciding what you see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use &lt;a href=&quot;https://feeder.co/&quot;&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt; as my RSS reader, it’s open-source
and has been great IMO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacytools.io/privacy-rss-feed-readers&quot;&gt;PrivacyTools privacy-rss-feed-readers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS Feeds&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Feeder, you click the 3 dots in the top right and click + Add feed, you can
then type the regular address of a site &amp;amp; if it has RSS feeds, Feeder will list
them. Most sites that have an RSS feed will have an orange RSS button that you
can click on to get the address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PrivacyTools: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacytools.io/guides/rss.xml&quot;&gt;https://www.privacytools.io/guides/rss.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darknet Diaries: &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcast.darknetdiaries.com/&quot;&gt;https://podcast.darknetdiaries.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hacker News: &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/rss&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/rss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PrivacyGuides: &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacyguides.org/rss/&quot;&gt;https://privacyguides.org/rss/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tor Project blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.torproject.org/feed.xml&quot;&gt;https://blog.torproject.org/feed.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mozilla Security Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mozilla.org/security/feed/&quot;&gt;https://blog.mozilla.org/security/feed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MDN Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/blog/rss.xml&quot;&gt;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/blog/rss.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F-Droid Forum - Latest posts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.f-droid.org/posts.rss&quot;&gt;https://forum.f-droid.org/posts.rss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opensource.com: &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/feed&quot;&gt;https://opensource.com/feed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DuckDuckGo Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://spreadprivacy.com/rss/&quot;&gt;https://spreadprivacy.com/rss/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic Frontier Foundation Deeplinks Blog:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/rss/updates.xml&quot;&gt;https://www.eff.org/rss/updates.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KrebsonSecurity: &lt;a href=&quot;https://krebsonsecurity.com/feed/&quot;&gt;https://krebsonsecurity.com/feed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkenfox recent commits:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/arkenfox/user.js/commits/master.atom&quot;&gt;https://github.com/arkenfox/user.js/commits/master.atom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkenfox release notes: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/arkenfox/user.js/releases.atom&quot;&gt;https://github.com/arkenfox/user.js/releases.atom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brave Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://brave.com/blog/index.xml&quot;&gt;https://brave.com/blog/index.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars Technica: &lt;a href=&quot;https://feeds.arstechnica.com/arstechnica/index/&quot;&gt;https://feeds.arstechnica.com/arstechnica/index/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PrivacySavvy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacysavvy.com/feed/&quot;&gt;https://privacysavvy.com/feed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PrivacySavvy Security Archive: &lt;a href=&quot;https://privacysavvy.com/security/feed/&quot;&gt;https://privacysavvy.com/security/feed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://research.cloudflare.com/projects/network-privacy/odns/&quot;&gt;Oblivious DNS over HTTPS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ietf.org/archive/id/draft-denis-dprive-dnscrypt-06.html&quot;&gt;DNSCrypt Protocol&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacytools.io/&quot;&gt;PrivacyTools.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/04/30/in-praise-of-tor/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides In Praise of Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/en/advanced/tor-overview/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides Tor Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://orbot.app/en/&quot;&gt;Orbot app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orbot is a free app from the Guardian Project that empowers other apps on your
device to use the internet more securely. Orbot uses Tor to encrypt your
internet traffic and hide it by bouncing through a seris of computers around
the world.
–&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.torproject.org/glossary/orbot/&quot;&gt;TorProject Orbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://guardianproject.info/apps/org.torproject.android/&quot;&gt;Guardian Project Orbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WireGuard is an extremely simple yet fast and modern VPN that utilizes
state-of-the-art cryptography. –&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wireguard.com/&quot;&gt;Wireguard.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ssd.eff.org/&quot;&gt;EFF Surveillance Self Defense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coveryourtracks.eff.org/&quot;&gt;EFF Cover Your Tracks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amiunique.org/&quot;&gt;AmIUnique?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.net/&quot;&gt;What is NoScript?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacyguides.org/en/dns/&quot;&gt;PrivacyGuides DNS Recommendations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/dns/what-is-a-dns-server/&quot;&gt;What is a DNS Server?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/dns/what-is-anycast-dns/&quot;&gt;What is Anycast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dn.org/anycast-dns-vs-unicast-dns-a-comparative-guide/&quot;&gt;anycast-dns-vs-unicast-dns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ddos/glossary/user-datagram-protocol-udp/&quot;&gt;What is UDP?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Security/Transport_Layer_Security&quot;&gt;MDN TLS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ssl/transport-layer-security-tls/&quot;&gt;What is TLS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://network-guides.com/tcp-ip-basics/&quot;&gt;Networking-Guides TCP/IP Basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/dns/what-is-recursive-dns/&quot;&gt;Cloudflare What is recursive DNS?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/evilsocket/opensnitch&quot;&gt;OpenSnitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pi-hole/pi-hole&quot;&gt;pi-hole&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spyware.neocities.org/&quot;&gt;Sypware Watchdog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>fingerprinting</title><id>https://mako088.github.io/browsers/fingerprinting.html</id><updated>2025-10-27T11:33:55+00:00</updated><link href="https://mako088.github.io/browsers/fingerprinting.html" rel="alternate"/><content type="html"></content></entry></feed>