<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>privacy-book</title><link>https://mako088.github.io/</link><description>An mdBook-generated site</description><generator>mdbook-rss-feed 1.0.0</generator><item><title>Encrypted DNS on Arch</title><link>https://mako088.github.io/arch/enc_dns.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>❗ NOTE: There are many other ways for someone monitoring your traffic to see
what domain you looked up via DNS that it’s effectiveness is questionable
without also using Tor or a VPN. Encrypted DNS will not help you hide any of
your browsing activity.</p><pre><code class="language-bash">sudo pacman -S dnscrypt-proxy
</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p>NOTE: udp is required for dnscrypt protocol, keep this in mind when
configuring your servers if your output chain is a default drop.</p><p><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Dnscrypt-proxy">Arch Wiki dnscrypt-proxy</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://mako088.github.io/arch/enc_dns.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardening Arch</title><link>https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_arch.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>⚠️ Warning: I am not a security expert. This guide presents various options
for hardening Arch Linux, but it is your responsibility to evaluate whether
each adjustment suits your specific needs and environment. Security hardening
and process isolation can introduce stability challenges, compatibility
issues, or unexpected behavior. Additionally, these protections often come
with performance tradeoffs. Always conduct thorough research, there are no
plug and play one size fits all security solutions.</p><p>Much of this guide draws inspiration or recommendations from the well-known
<a href="https://madaidans-insecurities.github.io/guides/linux-hardening.html">Linux Hardening Guide</a>
by Madaidan’s Insecurities and the Arch Wiki. Arch is great but when anonymity
truly matters, use Whonix o]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_arch.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardening Firefox</title><link>https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_firefox.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Browser hardening</strong> focuses on reducing attack surface and blocking tracking
by disabling or restricting features like JavaScript, cookies, telemetry, and
third-party scripts.</p><p><strong>Fingerprint protection</strong>, on the other hand, aims to make your browser
indistinguishable from others. Instead of just blocking data collection, it
ensures that your browser’s configuration; screen size, fonts, user agent,
etc. matches a large group of users, so you blend in.</p><p><strong>Browser compartmentalization</strong> is a technique where different browsers are
dedicated to distinct online activities to isolate cookies, trackers, and
browsing data. For example, Mullvad Browser can be used solely for activities
where fingerprinting resistance is critical, such as anonymou]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://mako088.github.io/arch/hardening_firefox.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Encrypted Arch Install</title><link>https://mako088.github.io/arch/enc_install.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The ultimate installation resource is always goint to be the:</p><p><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Installation_guide">Arch Wiki Installation Guide</a></p><p><a href="https://archlinux.org/download/#checksums">Verify PGP Signatures</a>, the ISO
directory is just the same directory where your Arch Linux ISO file is stored.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://mako088.github.io/arch/enc_install.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>